<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
	<div class="main">
		
		<div class="two-thirds column">
			<p>There is no step-through debugger in the XSLT/XPath extesnion. When debugging XSLT, the <strong>xsl:message</strong> instruction can be used to send output to the terminal window.
				Another popular approach is 
				to add XSLT instructions that insert diagnostics information directly into the result document. 			
			</p>
			<h3>Diagnosing state of in-scope XSLT variables</h3>
			<p>There is special provision for conveniently reviewing the state of in-scope XSLT variables. This approach is outlined here.</p>
			<h4>1. Use Auto-complete for xsl:message</h4>
			<p>To assist with debugging, the XSLT editor has special auto-completion for the xsl:message instruction:</p>
			<p>
				<img src="resources/xslmessage-list.png" class="scale-with-grid" />
			</p>
			<h4>2. Review Inserted xsl:message</h4>
			<p>When <strong>complex variables</strong> is selected from the auto-complete list,
				an xsl:message snippet will be inserted at the cursor with all the in-scope variables listed.
				A title is automativally inserted into the xsl:message block. This corresponds to the name or mode of the parent instruction,
				such as the name of an enclosing xsl:function or the mode of an xsl:template.
			</p>
			<p>
				<img src="resources/inserted-message.png" class="scale-with-grid" />
			</p>
			<h4>3. QuickFix imported library function</h4>
			<p>
				As can be seen in the image above the library XPath function <code>ext:print()</code> is included within a
				Text Value Template (TVT) adjacent to each variable that is added in the current scope.
				When inserted for the first time, the inserted functions will be marked as 'problems'. Hover over the
				problem function and accept the 'QuickFix' by pressing <span class="shortcut">Enter</span>.
			</p>
			<p>The QuickFix will insert a namespace declaration for the <strong>'ext'</strong> prefix along
				with an <strong>xsl:include</strong> instruction to import the XSLT library where this function is defined.
				The <strong>href</strong> attribute for the instruction is set to the path of the 
				<strong>xpath-result-serializer.xsl</strong> library module. If the library module is found in
				the workspace folder then this file path will be used, otherwise it is set to reference the
				library module installed with this extension.
			</p>
			<p>
				<img src="resources/extprint-quickfix.png" class="scale-with-grid" />
			</p>
			<h4>4. Run XSLT and Review State in Terminal</h4>
			<p>
				You can now <a href="run-xslt.html">run the XSLT</a> as normal, but you will now see the xsl:message output in the terminal
				window for each variable. Each type is serialized in a form optimised for diagnostics. If using a version of Saxon prior to v0.9.0.2 the output
				will be colorised also:
			</p>
			<p>
				<p>
					<img src="resources/printed-map.png" class="scale-with-grid" />
				</p>
			</p>
			<p><aside>Colorising is restricted to a limited set of Saxon versions because later versions don't support use of a built-in
				TextEmitter command-line option. This option is needed to preventing the escaping of ANSI codes used for coloring the output.<br/>
				In later saxon versions, a <strong>MessageHandler</strong> can be used to achieve the same thing but this must be done using 
					Saxon's Java API.	
				</aside>
			</p>
		</div>
		
	</div>	
</html>