<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
	<div class="main">
		
		<div class="two-thirds column">
			<p>
				The <a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/editor/codebasics">Visual Studio Code  User Guide</a>
				should be your main resource for learning about general editor features and how to use them effectively.</p>
			<p>This page provides a high level guide from an XML editing or reviewing perspective. See the <a href="editing-xslt.html">Editing&#160;XSLT/XPath</a>
			page for more language-specific help on these languages.</p>
			<h3>XML Elements</h3>
			<h5>Change Element Tag Name</h5>
		  As you edit the start tag name of an element, the corresponding end tag name is changed at the same time to
			keep the XML well-nested.
			<h5>Self-Close Element</h5>
			<p>
				To convert an element with a start-tag and end-tag to a self-closed element: With the cursor immediately to the
				left of the <code>&gt;</code>at the end of the start-tag, type 
				<code>/</code>. Any element contents and the
				end tag will be deleted automatically:
			</p>
			<code class="block"><![CDATA[<d><para]]><span style="color: red; font-weight: bold">/</span>&gt;<![CDATA[test</para</d>
--> <d><para]]><span style="color: red; font-weight: bold">/</span><![CDATA[></d> ]]></code>
			<h5>Rename all elements with selected name</h5>
			<p>
				Select the element tag name you want to rename by double-clicking it, then press (<span class="shortcut">⇧⌘L</span>). This selects
				all matching tag names so you're in a multi-cursor edit mode. As you edit the tag name you selected all
				matching tag names are edited also. When done, press <span class="shortcut">Escape to exit multi-cursor edit</span>.
			</p>
			<h3>Intellisense</h3>
			<p>Outside of the extension intellisense features for XSLT and XPath, a small set of snippets for general purpose XML elements is accessible
			from the intellisense suggestions list.</p>
			<p>
				With the cursor in the element start tag where you wish to add the attribute, press <span class="shortcut">⌃Space</span>
				and select <code>attribute</code> to insert the code snippet:
			</p>
			<code class="block"><bold>name</bold>="<bold>value</bold>"</code>
			<p>Edit the <code>name</code> and then press <span class="shortcut">Tab</span> to edit the <code>value</code>.</p>
			<h3 id="xmlformatting">XML Formatting</h3>
			<p>When you have an XML file open, normal XML formatting features are available. With typical hand-edited XML, it is
			only indentation that is correct by the formatting. However, if no newline characters are found at the start of the XML file,
				it is assumed the contents is system generated and newline characters are added for elements that are not mixed content.</p>
			<p>The formatter observes the normal rules for whitespace preservation in XML. So <code>xml:space</code> attributes affect
			whether indentation is preserved. Whitespace in <code>CDATA</code> sections and 'significant' whitespace in content inferred
				to be <em>mixed content</em> is also preserved.</p>
			<p>XML attributes on newlines and multi-line attribute value are indented by the XML formatting provider to reflect the level of nesting.</p>
			<h3>XML Element Selection</h3>
			<p>The XSLT/XPath extension provides a set of commands for selecting an element. 
				These commands can be invoked from the Command Palette (<span class="shortcut">⇧⌘L</span>).</p>
			<ul>
				<li><strong>Goto XPath</strong> - navigate to the element/attribute given by the XPath </li>
				<li><strong>Select current element</strong> - extend selection to include containing element's start/end tags</li>
				<li><strong>Select parent element</strong> - extend selection to include parent element's start/end tags</li>
				<li><strong>Select following element</strong> - extend selection to include next sibling's start/end tags</li>
				<li><strong>Select preceding element</strong> - extend selection to include previous sibling's start/end tags</li>
			</ul>			
		</div>
		
	</div>	
</html>