<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
	<div class="main">
		
		<div class="two-thirds column">
			<p>
				The comprehensive <a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/editor/codebasics">User Guide</a>
				for the Visual Studio Code editor should be your primary resource for learning about editor features
				and how to use them effectively.</p>
			<p>This section provides extra information specific to the XSLT/XPath extension environment,
				and also emphasizes features that may be particularly useful from the XSLT or XPath coders perspective.</p>
			<h3>XML Elements</h3>
			<h5>Change Element Tag Name</h5>
		  As you edit the start tag name of an element, the corresponding end tag name is changed at the same time to
			keep the XML well-nested.
			<h5>Self-Close Element</h5>
			<p>
				To convert an element with a start-tag and end-tag to a self-closed element: With the cursor immediately to the
				left of the <code>&gt;</code>at the end of the start-tag, type 
				<code>/</code>. Any element contents and the
				end tag will be deleted automatically:
			</p>
			<code class="block"><![CDATA[<d><para]]><span style="color: red; font-weight: bold">/</span>&gt;<![CDATA[test</para</d>
--> <d><para]]><span style="color: red; font-weight: bold">/</span><![CDATA[></d> ]]></code>
			<h5>Rename all elements with selected name</h5>
			<p>
				Select the element tag name you want to rename by double-clicking it, then press (<span class="shortcut">⇧⌘L</span>). This selects
				all matching tag names so you're in a multi-cursor edit mode. As you edit the tag name you selected all
				matching tag names are edited also. When done, press <span class="shortcut">Escape to exit multi-cursor edit</span>.
			</p>
			<aside>Note: This is a standard Visual Studio Command so the <em>Find</em> is not XML-aware.</aside>
			<h5>Intellisense</h5>
			<p>Outside of the extension intellisense features for XSLT and XPath, a small set of snippets for general purpose XML elements is accessible
			from the intellisense suggestions list.</p>
			<p>
				With the cursor in the element start tag where you wish to add the attribute, press <span class="shortcut">⌃Space</span>
				and select <code>attribute</code> to insert the code snippet:
			</p>
			<code class="block"><bold>name</bold>="<bold>value</bold>"</code>
			<p>Edit the <code>name</code> and then press <span class="shortcut">Tab</span> to edit the <code>value</code>.</p>
			<h3>Code Formatting</h3>
			<p>When you have an XML file open, normal XML formatting features are available. Normally, it is
			only indentation that is affected, but, if no newlines are found at the start of the XML file,
			new lines are added too.</p>
		</div>
		
	</div>	
</html>