<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
	<div class="main">
		
		<div class="two-thirds column">
			<p>Visual Studio Code includes a compelling set of features for code navigation, 
				the language-neutral details are outlined here <a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/editor/editingevolved">here</a>.</p>
			<p>This page outlines code navigation from an XSLT and XPath development perspective.</p>
			<h3>File Navigation</h3>
			<p>
				While the Explorer View is used for workspace browsing, pressing <span class="shortcut">⌘P</span>, for the <strong>Quick Open</strong>
				command, provides a quick-pick list of available files that is filtered/highlighted as you type.
			</p>
			<p>File tabs are arranged in one or more Editor Groups. Editor Groups are arranged either adjacent or above/below other Editor groups.
			The same file may be open in more than one Editor Group. There are settings to control whether file tabs are scrollable or wrapped
				within an Editor Group.</p>
			<p>Hold <span class="shortcut">Ctrl</span> and press <span class="shortcut">Tab</span> for a list of files in an Editor Group. Keep pressing
			<span class="shortcut">Tab</span> until you reach the file you want and then release <span class="shortcut">Ctrl</span> to open it.</p>
			<h5>Previous/Next Location</h5>
			<p>Many actions can be used to navigate you to a new location. Press <span class="shortcut">⌃-</span> for <strong>Previous Location</strong> and <span class="shortcut">⌃⇧-</span> for
			<strong>Next Location</strong>. Locations may be in the same file or different files.</p>
			<h5>File Links</h5>
			<p>In XSLT, The <code>href</code> attribute values of <code>xsl:import</code> and <code>xsl:include</code> have a solid underline if the file path is resolved.
			Press <span class="shortcut">⌘+Click</span> on the file path to navigate to that file.</p>
			<h3>XSLT/XML BreadCrumbs</h3>
			<p>
				The BreadCrumb View, shown at the top of the editor, shows the current element or attribute location
				within an XML or XSLT file with respect to ancestor elements. In XSLT Breadcrumbs, an identifier is often shown as well as the element name.
				This may be for example the <code>name</code> of an <code>xsl:variable</code> or the <code>mode</code> of an <code>xsl:template</code>.
				The symbol names are the same as those shown in the Outline view.
			</p>
			<p>Clicking on a BreadCrumb item will show a dropdown outline view which you can then navigate through with the mouse, touch or cursor keys.</p>
			<h5>Keyboard Navigation</h5>
			<p>
				Press <span class="shortcut">⇧⌘.</span> (note the 'dot' character) to select the last Breadcrumb item and open <strong>with</strong> a dropdown outline. 
				You can then use cursor keys
				to navigate the dropdown outline. Alternatively, press <span class="shortcut">⇧⌘;</span> (note the 'semi-colon' character) 
				to select the last Breadcrumb item <strong>without</strong> a dropdown outline. 
				Use the <span class="shortcut">←</span> and <span class="shortcut">→</span> keys to select a BreadCrumb item or the
				<span class="shortcut">↓</span> for the dropdown outline.
			</p>
			<aside>Note: You can toggle the BreadCrumbs view on/off but if the BreadCrumbs view is disabled this will also disable XML, XSLT or XPath Warnings and Errors.
				The Code Checker depends on the symbol name provider that BreadCrumbs invokes.</aside>
			<h3>Outline View</h3>
			<p>
				The <a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/getstarted/userinterface#_outline-view">Outline View</a> orTree View is a panel shown at the bottom
				of the File Explorer. It shows the XML or XSLT document element tree, symbol names in the tree include my include element identifiers such
				as the <code>mode</code> for an <code>xsl:template</code>.
			</p>
			<p>Symbols in the Outline View can be sorted by position, name or category. There's also a '<strong>Filter on Type</strong>' mode that
			filters the Outline View while you type in part of a symbol name.</p>
			<h3>Goto Definition</h3>
			<p>
				Invoke the <strong>Goto Defintion</strong> command by pressing (<span class="shortcut">F12</span>) on any symbol name such as a variable or function name.
				This command navigates you to the location of the symbol definition (for example, the corresponding <code>xsl:variable</code> instruction),
				opening the containing file in the editor group if not already open.
			</p>
			<h3>Peek Defintion</h3>
			<p>Invoke the <strong>Peek</strong> command by pressing (<span class="shortcut">⌥F12</span>) on any symbol name such as a variable or function name.
				This command embeds a view of the defintion inline avoiding the context-switch arising from the <strong>Goto Definition</strong> command.
				The inline definition view permits quick edits of the defintion also. Press <span class="shortcut">Escape</span> to close the definition view.
			</p>
		</div>
		
	</div>	
</html>