<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
	<div class="main">
		
		<div class="two-thirds column">
			<p>XSLT 4.0 currently comprises a set of draft proposals maintained by 
				the <a href="https://qt4cg.org">W3C XSLT 4.0 Community group</a>.</p>
			
			<p>DeltaXignia's XSLT/XPath language extension provides high-level support
				for XSLT 4.0 as implemented in Saxon 12.0 and documented 
				<a href="https://www.saxonica.com/documentation12/index.html#!v4extensions">here</a>.</p>
			
			
			<p>Note that, given the independent release cycles for Saxon and the XSLT 4.0 draft, there will be
				differences between the implementation and the draft specification. Some parts of the
				specification are likely to change significantly before it is finalized.
			</p>
			<p>We will endeavour to keep this extension up to date with the latest Saxon XSLT 4.0 implementation.
			Earlier versions of XSLT 4.0 will not be supported for auto-completion and linting.	
			</p>
			
			<h3>Editing XSLT 4.0</h3>
			<p>The <strong>version</strong> attribute on the stylesheet root element controls the
				XSLT version supported by the linter and for auto-completion. When the 
				version attribute on the stylesheet root element is set to <strong>4.0</strong>,
				auto-completion for XSLT instructions and attributes and XPath functions will be included.
				
			</p>
			<p>
				<img src="resources/xslt40-completion.png" class="scale-with-grid" />
			</p>
			<h3>Running XSLT 4.0</h3>
			<p>When invoking SaxonJ (Java) for XSLT 4.0 with an <a href="run-xslt.html">XSLT task</a> from VS Code, 
				the <strong>allowSyntaxExtensions40</strong> must be set <strong>on</strong>
				in the task defined in tasks.json. The task invokes Saxon via its command-line
				interface with the configuration property <code>--allowSyntaxExtensions:on</code>. 
			</p>
			<aside>			 
				The free Saxon-HE version <strong>does not</strong> support the language extensions
				for XSLT 4.0. You will need to reference a Saxon-PE or Saxon-EE Jar file (with license file)
				in the <strong>saxonJar</strong> property of the task definition.
			</aside>
			<hr/>
			<h3>Other Editors for XSLT 4.0</h3>
            <p>The <a href="https://www.oxygenxml.com/xml_editor/whatisnew25.0.html">Oxygen XML 25.0 editor</a> also provides
				language support for XSLT 4.0. It supports
				the earlier <strong>Saxon 11</strong> implementation of XSLT 4.0.</p>
			
				<p>While Oxygen does need to be <a href="https://www.oxygenxml.com/xml_editor/buy_oxygen_xml_editor.html">purchased</a>,
				it has the advantage of including Saxon-EE built-in, so you will not need to purchase Saxon
				separately. Major versions of Oxygen are normally released annually so the next update is expected in October 2023.
				Oxygen XML provides an integrated solution for XML developers 
				and content authors, and hosts an <a href="https://www.oxygenxml.com/xml_editor.html">array of other features</a>.
			</p>
		</div>
		
	</div>	
</html>